Guide to the Vladimir and Véra Nabokov publishing correspondence, 1945-1977.
Nabokov, Vladimir and Véra publishing correspondence, 1945-1977
- Series IV. Outgoing Correspondence from Véra Nabokov 1949-1977
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, July 24, 1972 to October 27, 1972. (Box 6, Folder 26)
    6 TLS, in English and French, requesting changes to the Gallimard contract, especially regarding the value-added tax (VN finds it "incredibly mean" of Gallimard to expect VN to pay this), noting the absurdity of the continued impasse between VN and New Directions over Sebastian Knight, and the slow pace of Chahine's translation of Ada.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, November 7, 1972 to February 26, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 27)
    6 TLS (1 signed in Russian), in English and French, requesting changes to the contract with Gallimard. VN will back down if so advised by Schébéko, as he knows Gallimard is a man of principle, but "somehow all his principles work to his material advantage" (2.19.73). Notes that VN has found a potential translator for Transparent Things, and commiserates about the back problem they share.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, February 23, 1973 to June 1, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 28)
    7 TLS, 1 TL with attached letter to Nicole Ouali (Gallimard), in English and French, regarding the paperback contracts with Gallimard for Lolita, Pnin, The Defense, the cover design for Pnin (VN objects to the use of the American flag as floor covering, given the recent flag-burning incidents in the US), and Chaïns' translation of Ada. Autograph postscript to 2.23.73.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, June 13, 1973 to August 30, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 29)
    5 TLS, in English and French, regarding the VNs' taxes, and various paperback cover designs (for Pnin and The Defense), and agreeing to initiate proceedings against Kersovani.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, September 10, 1973 to October 17, 1973. (Box 6, Folder 30)
    7 TLS, one of which is typed on a letter to Prins, 1 autograph note apologizing to Schébéko for "the dreadful cold potatoes" and signed in Russian. Rest of correspondence deals with contractual and accounting matters.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, November 28, 1973 to January 2, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 31)
    6 TLS, in English and French, regarding various contractual matters (especially the new publication of Lolita in Portuguese, the simultaneous publication of Transparent Things and Ada, and the situation with Grasset), and expressing VN's disapproval of the proposed cover for The Defense (VN complains that Luzhin does not look at all like the man on the cover, not being nearly so handsome nor likely to go nude). Two autograph postscripts.
  - Typed copy of translations by Donald Harper and Jean-Bernard Blandenier, with corrections, dated January 7, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 32)
    Typed copy of translation samples for Transparent Things, with corrections by VN to Harper's sample.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, February 1, 1974 to April 1, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 33)
    6 TLS, in English, expressing VN's delight that Harper has been signed to do the translation of Transparent Things and his hatred of Festivals, Committees and so on, and negotiations with Dr. Bloch (whom Véra does not trust) and Abril.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, April 3, 1974 to May 20, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 34)
    8 TLS, in English, regarding various contractual matters for Lolita (especially foreign publication of both a paperback edition and a screenplay adaptation by VN), Laughter in the Dark and King, Queen, Knave, expressing disgust at publicity tactics of their vacation hotel, and agreeing to the visit (from Fayard) of Messrs. de Fallois and Hell.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, May 22, 1974 to August 23, 1974. (Box 6, Folder 35)
    7 TLS with copy of a check, in English, concerning various contractual matters (especially the foreign publication of Lolita and the contract with Gallimard for King, Queen, Knave), as well as the upcoming simultaneous publication of Ada and Transparent Things. Mentions Orengo's death. Autograph postscript to 6.3.74.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, November 8, 1974 to January 27, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 36)
    8 TLS, in English, regarding various contractual matters for Lolita, Strong Opinions, Look at the Harlequins! and Laughter in the Dark. Also mentions the transfer of rights from the Vladimir VN Literary Trust to Dmitri VN. Véra declares Prins a "crook." Autograph postscript to 11.2.74.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, February 5, 1975 to June 16, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 37)
    7 TLS, 1 autograph note, in Russian and English, re various publication details of the paperback edition of King, Queen, Knave, the launching of Ada (VN agrees to interviews held in Paris, for which expenses Véra bills Clairouin in attachment to 6.5.75), the contract with Fayard for Look at the Harlequins!, and the actions of the "crook" Prins. Mentions transfer of rights from the Trust to Dmitri. Autograph postscript in Russian to 5.2.75.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko and D. Develdère, June 16, 1975 to November 26, 1975. (Box 6, Folder 38)
    9 TLS, in French and English, regarding the publication of Ada and Look at the Harlequins! by Fayard, as well as the foreign publication of Lolita by Grijalbo, and other contractual matters.Mentions that "Mr. Girodias is riding high again" (8.1.75).
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, December 8, 1975 to February 18, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 39)
    6 TLS and 1 TL to Juan Grijalbo (a copy for Schébéko), with photocopy of contract, 1 autograph note on the copy of a TL by VN to Alex Grall, in English and French, re contractual matters (the Brazilian rights to Look at the Harlequins!, and Grijalbo's paperback contract for Lolita), and two letters outlining who owns which of VN's works. The latter (2.18.76) refers to a "heartrending conversation" between Schébéko and Véra.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, February 23, 1976 to April 26, 1976. (Box 6, Folder 40)
    7 TLS, noting the receipt of the first part of the Look at the Harlequins! French translation, contractual and publication matters for various short stories, as well as Bend Sinister.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, June 6, 1976 to January 3, 1977. (Box 6, Folder 41)
    5 TLS, in English, including a letter from Jacqueline Callier, VN's secretary to James Laughlin (New Directions), and a copy of a letter from Laughlin to VN, announcing that the deadlock over Sebastian Knight with New Directions has been broken, and regarding various other contractual matters, including the translation and publication of VN's stories by Juilliard. Notes that VN is feeling a little better, especially when he gets some sleep (which is not very often), and briefly acknowledges that there has been no change in Véra's own condition.
  - Correspondence from Véra Nabokov to Marie Schébéko, with typed corrections, February 25, 1977 to June 15, 1977. (Box 6, Folder 42)
    5 TLS, 2 sheets of typed corrections to the French translation of Look at the Harlequins!, in English, regarding various contractual matters.
- Series V. Correspondence to and from Clairouin 1947-1977
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, April 16, 1947 to September 12, 1947. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    11 TL, in French, to VN (5), Grasset (2), Table Rond (1), Gallimard (1). Mostly regarding the film rights for Laughter in the Dark, which VN has sold to an American company but which apparently belong to Grasset and Ergaz, and the placement of The Defense, Gogol and Invitation with French firms. Ergaz cites the current "crisis" as reason for the delay in so placing VN's works.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, October 21, 1947 to April 26, 1949. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    9 TL, in French, from Ergaz to VN (4), VN (1), Albin Michel (1), Fayard (1), Jarl Priel (1). Letter from Jarl Priel to Ergaz asking after the publication status of Invitation. Reiterates how much effort Ergaz is putting into getting VN's works published, but also notes the difficulty in publishing even works of the first order at this time (especially after a "very stupid article" by Sartre on the subject of one of VN's earlier works. Discusses some translation issues, including the fact that not all share the VNs' high opinion of Priel.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, May 10, 1949 to August 1, 1949. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    7 TL, in French, to VN (6) and Albin Michel (1). Autograph note from Yvonne Davet enclosing a sample of her translation of Sebastian Knight. Somewhat exasperated series of letters attempting to persuade VN that Ergaz is working hard on behalf of his remarkable work, and that it is truly difficult to find editors willing to publish new work at this time. Deals primarily with the contract (with Albin Michel) for Sebastian Knight.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, November 21, 1950 to October 3, 1951. (Box 7, Folder 4)
    9 TL in French and English, to VN (8) and New Directions (1). Mostly regarding the French publication of Sebastian Knight, delayed by the proposed publication of the novel in a magazine, La Table Rond, as well as the republication of The Defense. Ergaz tries to defend Davet against VN's "severe" criticisms, and wonders whether he is absolutely against using her for translation of Conclusive Evidence, as Ergaz feels Davet may be hurt by a refusal.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, October 26, 1951 to February 15, 1952. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    11 TLS, to VN (5), Fayard (1), Grasset (2), Plon (3, one of which is a copy), in French. Mostly regarding the contract with Table Rond/Plon for the publication of all of VN's works (or at least 5: Conclusive Evidence, Gogol, Invitation, The Gift and The Defense), and the question of the film rights for Laughter in the Dark.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, March 27, 1952 to July 26, 1952. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    12 TL, in French and German, to VéN (7), Fr. Schlaich (1), Büchergilde Gutenberg (1), M. de Venloo (1), Les nouvelles littéraires (1), with copy of letter sent to VN by Gallimard. Regarding contract difficulties with Gallimard, who have refused options on Conclusive Evidence and Bend Sinister, yet apparently retain rights to all of VN's works, thus potentially fouling up the contract with Table Rond. Mentions the interest of an American publisher in The Defense.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, July 30, 1952 to August 24, 1954. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    9 TL, in English and French, to VN (2), VéN (4), Table Rond (2), Julie Kernan (1). Mostly regarding various contractual, publication, and translation matters, especially the contract with Table Rond, and Marcelle Sibon's translation of Gogol, for which VN submits an enormous list of corrections (to what Ergaz fears will be Sibon's embarrassment). In 8.24.54, Ergaz notes that she has forgotten to address the Nabokovs' questions about the "novel that Monsieur Nabokov cannot publish in America," but is very much interested in this novel and believes she knows a firm that has published works in English outside of both England and the US.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, February 8, 1955 to June 15, 1955. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    8 TL with telegram message, in French and English, to VN. Mostly regarding the film rights to Laughter in the Dark, and the contract with Girodias for Lolita. Ergaz, in introducing G. as a possible publisher, maintains that they need not worry about the quality of his firm's books, and mentions that Olympia has just published The Story of O. G. apparently not only thinks Lolita of immense literary value, but thinks it may help to alter society's attitude towards the "love described in Lolita" (5.13.55).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, July 20, 1955 to December 27, 1955. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    10 TL, in French, to VN. Mostly concerning the English publication of Lolita (especially the question of copyright), as well as the need to find a French publisher for the novel (perhaps Pauvert, perhaps Gallimard). Ergaz is confident that G. will do well by Lolita, as he has gained a lot of experience through his publication of The Story of O. Also mentions the potential publication of The Defense by Le Club du Meilleur Livre and the launching of Conclusive Evidence in France.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 1956 to June 27, 1956. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    9 TL, 1 statement, in French, to VN (3) and VéN (5), and Michèle Manceaux of L'Express (1). Mostly regarding the foreign translation and publication of Lolita (into French with Gallimard, Swedish with Bonnier, and Danish with Reitzel). Ergaz believes it important to publish Lolita. with a firm like Gallimard, as Pauvert (associated with Olympia) has a certain reputation based on its publication of works such as The Story of O (which Ergaz feels has no literary value). To Manceaux, who has just completed an article on Lolita. she writes that Lolita. is not a work of pornography, and is not about the love of an "old man" for a little girl, but rather a man's love for a woman (3.2.56). Ergaz is beginning to find G. slippery and untrustworthy.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, July 24, 1956 to November 29, 1956. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    11 TL, to VN (5) and VéN (6), in French. Mostly regarding the publication of Conclusive Evidence and The Defense by Table Rond, and foreign contracts for Lolita. Charts the beginning of the dispute between VN and Girodias over the matter of American publication. Among other things, G. tells Ergaz - falsely - that he is bound by the terms of his contract with VN not to negotiate contracts without VN's knowledge. Mentions potential publication of extracts of Lolita. in The Anchor Review.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, December 19, 1956 to March 6, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    8 TL to VéN, with 1 statement, in French, regarding the ban on 20 books published by Olympia, including Lolita. Notes especially the general outrage that a book so obviously non-pornographic as Lolita should have been banned. Much detail surrounding Girodias' actions, and response of the press, writers, editors to the government's actions.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, March 13, 1957 to April 30, 1957. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    10 TL, to VN (5) and VéN (5), in French. Mostly regarding the publication of all of VN's works in French if not with Table Rond, which is in difficulties, then with Gallimard (VN is somewhat exasperated that his books are not appearing at a time when everybody is talking about him). Encourages VN to take up Girodias' offer and launch legal proceedings on behalf of Lolita. (cites Graham Greene's support of such a plan). Also discusses Girodias' position(s) with regard to the publication of Lolita in the US (G. apparently does not believe that Doubleday will ever get up the courage to publish Lolita.). Discusses possible translators for Lolita. and foreign contracts with Rowohlt and Mondadori. Asks whether, as has been rumored, VN has decided to allow Doubleday (rather than Clairouin) to represent future works. Autograph postscript to 4.16.57.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, May 20, 1957 to September 30, 1957. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    11 TL to VN (6) and VéN (5), in French. Mostly regarding the Girodias affair (includes assessments of G.'s character/personality), as well as foreign publication rights and the Kahane translation of Lolita. Mentions possibility that Graham Greene may interest Bodley Head in Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, October 2, 1957 to November 13, 1957. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    10 TL, to VN (5) and VéN (5), in French. Expresses first confusion over discrepancies between VN and G.'s accounts of their dispute, and then anger over G.'s behaviour. Ergaz consoles herself with the thought that there was no other publisher willing to launch Lolita, and advises against attempting to announce the contract with Olympia ruptured, as Olympia has gained a great deal of sympathy with the literary community. Discusses foreign contracts for Lolita as well as the contracts with Gallimard for Conclusive Evidence and Pnin (which will be translated by Chrestien).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, November 21, 1957 to February 4, 1958. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    8 TL, in French, to VN (7) and VéN (1), with 1 statement, and a copy of a letter from Michel Mohrt to Eric Kahane (dated 11.15.57) concerning the Lolita translation. Discusses slow pace of the Lolita translation, the contract with Gallimard for Pnin (to which VN objects), and the ongoing dispute with Girodias (Ergaz visits her lawyer friend Motulsky in early January, and he counsels against a legal proceeding seeking a rupture with Olympia).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, February 21, 1958 to June 23, 1958. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    10 TL, in French, to VN (3) and VéN (7), with 1 autograph calculation mostly concerning Gallimard's slow consideration of Invitation, various foreign contracts for Lolita (especially for the British publication) as well as Kahane's translation of the novel (interrupted by illness), and Weidenfeld and Nicolson's offer to publish all of VN's works in England.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, June 26, 1958 to October 15, 1958. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    11 TL, in French, to VN (1), VéN (9), and the VNs jointly (1), and 2 copies of an English telegram sent to VN. Regarding the negotiations with Bodley and Weidenfeld for the British publication of Lolita (includes discussion of the firms' respective thoughts on the possibility of prosecution), the French translation of Lolita, and Gallimard's decision to publish Invitation.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, October 17, 1958 to November 14, 1958. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    10 TL, in French, to VN (1), VéN (7), the Mexican Cultural Attaché (1), and 1 TL from the Cultural Attaché to Ergaz. Discusses foreign contracts for Lolita, as well as the pirated Mexican edition of Lolita. and the possibility of Rowohlt making an offer for more of VN's works (perhaps Invitation, The Defense and Sebastian Knight). Details Girodias' sudden demand that the British contract for Lolita include Calder, and the status of the new obscenity proceedings against Lolita.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, November 15, 1958 to December 31, 1958. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    15 TL, in French and English, to VéN, regarding foreign contracts for Lolita, the ongoing obscenity proceedings against Lolita in France, and the contract with Gallimard for Invitation.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, September 11, 1959 to February 1, 1960. (Box 7, Folder 21)
    7 TL, in French, to VN (1), VéN (5), and Aydin Yayinevi (1), regarding foreign contracts for Lolita and other novels, the film rights for Laughter in the Dark, the publication of some of VN's short stories, ("That in Aleppo Once", "Spring in Fialta"), and Gallimard's publication of VN's works (especially The Defense).
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, February 2, 1960 to March 24, 1960. (Box 7, Folder 22)
    8 TL, in French, to VN (3), VéN (4), and Mondadori (1), with 1 statement, 1 autograph calculation, and 1 autograph record of a visit from VN. Discusses various contract and publication matters (including Gallimard's failure to send VN the final proofs of Invitation and the contract for The Defense). Mentions Olympia's legal difficulties with Odette Hummel.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, April 1960 to June 3, 1960. (Box 7, Folder 23)
    7 TL, in French, to VN (1) and VéN (6), with 1 typed sheet with the Nabokovs' contact information for April 1960, and 1 autograph note. Mostly regarding foreign contracts for Lolita, the contract with Gallimard for The Defense, and the translator for "That in Aleppo Once."
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, June 10, 1960 to July 21, 1960. (Box 7, Folder 24)
    11 TL, in French and English to VN (3), VéN (5), G. Lallia (1), René Algrin (1), A. Rattner (1), Sonia Slonim (1), with 1 autograph note and 1 TL from Don Wallace to Clairouin. Discusses the 5 pirated Lebanese editions of Lolita, various foreign contracts for Lolita, the possible placement of Sebastian Knight with Gallimard, and the contract with Gallimard for The Defense.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, July 26, 1960 to September 13, 1960. (Box 7, Folder 25)
    14 TL, in French and English, to VéN (6), René Algrin (2), Carlos Hirsh (3, one of which is a copy), and Don Wallace (1); from René Algrin to Clairouin (1), from Don Wallace to Clairouin (1). Discusses the action being taken by Algrin in the matter of the Lebanese pirated editions, Gallimard's proposed paperback edition of Lolita, SUR's failure to send Clairouin statements, and various foreign contracts for Lolita. (especially the Israeli editions).
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, September 15, 1960 to December 16, 1957. (Box 7, Folder 26)
    13 TL, in French and English, to VéN (9), René Algrin (1), Don Wallace (1), and from Chandra Das (1) and René Algrin (1), with 1 statement, 1 copy of a telegram, and 1 autograph note. Re: foreign editions of Lolita, the ongoing legal proceedings in Lebanon, as well as the French publication of Sebastian Knight and the proposed serialization of Conclusive Evidence. Details an attempt by Ergaz to procure a 'divorce' from Olympia, with a description of G. as infantile and machiavellian.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, January 5, 1961 to February 17, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 27)
    14 TL, to VN (1), VéN (10), Madame Orstig (1), Pierre Moxhet (1), René Algrin (1). Regarding the film rights to Laughter in the Dark (Ergaz hopes to snag Brigitte Bardot), foreign editions of Lolita (including the pirated Mexican edition), and the dispute with Girodias, who wishes to resolve their disagreements via the courts, rather than "sans avocats", as VN desires.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, February 23, 1961 to July 1, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 28)
    13 TL, in French and English, to VN (3), VéN (4), René Algrin (1), le Dépôt Légal (2), the Editor of Playboy (1), and from René Algrin (2) and A. C. Spectorsky/Playboy (1). With 1 autograph note. Discusses various contractual and financial matters, the film rights to Laughter in the Dark (especially the Lombroso offer), and the Lebanese pirated editions. Ergaz answers VN's accusations in 4.19.61, and details the circumstances that led to Girodias feeling snubbed by VN at a party.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, July 7, 1961 to August 18, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 29)
    10 TL, in French, to VéN, with 1 autograph calculation on graph paper. Regarding various foreign editions of Lolita, the continuing dispute with Olympia, Gallimard's interest in VN's poems, the film rights to Laughter in the Dark, and Grasset's unsatisfactory sales of the same.
  - Correspondence from Clairouin, August 30, 1961 to October 26, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 30)
    9 TL, in French, to VéN (8), René Algrin (1), with 1 autograph note, and 1 typed sheet with extracts from Véra's letters. Discusses the contract with Lombroso for the film rights to Laughter in the Dark, the translation of The Defense, the publication and re-translation of "La visite au musée," and statements from Gallimard for Despair, Invitation, and Conclusive Evidence.
  - Correspondence to and from Clairouin, October 27, 1961 to November 21, 1961. (Box 7, Folder 31)